<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CODEBUG (Posts about machine-learning)</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://sijanb.com.np/categories/machine-learning.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:sijanonly@gmail.com"&gt;Sijan Bhandari&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 18:52:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>What is the trade-off between bias and variance in machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-the-trade-off-between-bias-and-variance-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Short:
A model with minimal parameters may exhibit high bias and low variance, while a model with numerous parameters may demonstrate high variance and low bias. Therefore, it is essential to achieve an optimal balance to avoid overfitting and underfitting the data. High bias arises from incorrect assumptions made by the learning algorithm, whereas variance arises from a model's sensitivity to minor variations in the training dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detail:
During development, all algorithms exhibit some degree of bias and variance. Models can be adjusted to address either bias or variance, but it is impossible to reduce both to zero without adversely affecting the other. This introduces the concept of the bias-variance trade-off.
Bias refers to the discrepancy between the average prediction of our model and the actual value being predicted, indicating the presence of systematic errors in the model.
Every algorithm inherently possesses some level of bias due to assumptions made within the model to simplify learning the target function. High bias can lead to underfitting, where the algorithm fails to capture relevant relationships between features and target outputs. Simpler algorithms tend to introduce more bias, whereas nonlinear algorithms usually have lower bias. These errors can originate from various sources, including the selection of training data, feature choices, or the training algorithm itself.
Variance measures how much a model's predictions change with different training sets, indicating the degree of over-specialization to a particular training set (overfitting). The goal is to assess the deviation of our model from the best possible model for the training data.
The ideal model seeks to minimize both bias and variance, achieving a balance that is neither too simple nor too complex, thereby yielding minimal error.
Low-variance models typically have a simple structure and are less sophisticated, but they risk being highly biased. Examples include Regression and Naive Bayes.
Conversely, low-bias models generally have a more flexible and complex structure but are prone to high variance. Examples include Nearest Neighbors and Decision Trees. Overfitting arises when a model is overly complex and learns the noise in the data rather than the actual signals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bias-variance-tradeoff</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-the-trade-off-between-bias-and-variance-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 18:51:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What are different types of gradient descent algorithm in machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-are-different-types-of-gradient-descent-algorithm-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;There exist three distinct types of gradient descent learning algorithms: batch gradient descent, stochastic gradient descent, and mini-batch gradient descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batch Gradient Descent (BGD)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Batch Gradient Descent, the term 'batch' signifies the utilization of the entire training dataset during each iteration of the learning process. By incorporating all training examples for each update, Batch Gradient Descent ensures stable error gradients and a consistent trajectory towards the optimal solution, albeit with significant computational demands.
This batching method enhances computational efficiency; however, it can still result in extended processing times for large training datasets due to the necessity of storing all data in memory. While Batch Gradient Descent typically yields a stable error gradient and reliable convergence, it occasionally converges to a local minimum rather than the global optimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD) enhances parameter updates by leveraging individual data points during each iteration. By conducting a training epoch for each dataset example and updating parameters sequentially, SGD minimizes memory requirements, as only a single training example needs to be stored at any given time. These frequent updates, while providing detailed and rapid adjustments, may lead to decreased computational efficiency relative to batch gradient descent. Despite the potential for noisy gradients, which arise from these frequent updates, this noise can facilitate the escape from local minima, thereby aiding in the pursuit of a global minimum. The principle of SGD is characterized by its utilization of a single example per iteration, hence the term "stochastic" reflects the random selection of each example within the batch. Given sufficient iterations, SGD proves effective, albeit with inherent noisiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini Batch Gradient Descent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini-batch gradient descent integrates principles from both batch gradient descent and stochastic gradient descent. It partitions the training dataset into smaller batch sizes and executes updates on each of these batches. This methodology achieves a balance between the computational efficiency of batch gradient descent and the rapidity of stochastic gradient descent. Similar to stochastic gradient descent, the average cost over epochs in mini-batch gradient descent exhibits fluctuations due to the averaging of a limited number of examples at a time.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>gradient-descent</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-are-different-types-of-gradient-descent-algorithm-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 17:12:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is underfitting in Machine Learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-underfitting-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Underfitting occurs in machine leanrning / data science when a data model fails to accurately capture the relationship between input and output variables, resulting in high error rates on both the training set and unseen data.
This also entails that the model has insufficient training duration or the input variables lack significance to establish a meaningful relationship between the input and output variables. As the model learns, its bias diminishes, but its variance may increase, leading to overfitting. The objective in model fitting is to identify the optimal balance between underfitting and overfitting (.i.e., finding the sweet spot), allowing the model to capture the dominant trend in the training data and generalize effectively to new datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;High biased model (underfitted) is not able to learn the very basic/important patterns in the training data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding more data and making your model simpler won't help to avoid underfitting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One should try other sophisticated models (e.g Decision tree in comparision to kNN) or add complexity in the current model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using complex models (example : polynomial regression rather than linear one) may be useful to capture the relevant patterns in the training data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding more features (or derived features from existing one) will also increase the model capacity and helps to avoid underfitting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you see unacceptably high training error and test error, the model is underfitted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;High bias and low variance are the indicators of underfitting models.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Underfitting is easier to track than overfitting since the performance can be measured during training phase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>high-bias</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><category>underfitting</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-underfitting-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 19:40:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is overfitting in Machine Learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-overfitting-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Overfitting occurs when the model attempts to match the training set too closely. On fresh data, the overfitted model is unable to produce accurate predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The model will attempt to match the data too closely and will pick up on noise in the data when the training data set is limited or the given model is complex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;An overfitted model picks up patterns that are unique to the training set and overlooks the generic patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regularization can reduce overfitting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overfitting can also be decreased by training on a large and diversed training data points.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overfitting can be detected by high variation .i.e, if the test data has a high error rate while the training data has a low error rate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A high variance model will overfit the data and is flexible in capturing every detail—relevant or not—and noise in the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A high variance model is also indicated as: Training error &amp;lt;&amp;lt; Validation error.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;More training data will improve the generalization of the given model and avoids overfitting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>high-variance</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><category>overfitting</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-overfitting-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 11:53:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is gradient descent ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-gradient-descent/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Gradient descent is a widely used optimization approach for training machine learning models and neural networks. Optimization is the process of minimizing or increasing an objective function.
Optimization entails calculating the gradient (partial derivatives) of the cost function for each parameter (weights and biases). To do this, the models are given training data iteratively.
And, the gradient points are determined. The gradient represents the steepest rise in the function. Gradient descent lowers cost function values by going in the opposite direction of the steepest decrease.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>gradient-descent</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-gradient-descent/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2024 07:02:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Inductive Bias in Machine Learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-inductive-bias-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;An explicit or implicit assumption or prior information about the model that permits it to generalize
outside of the training set of data is known as inductive bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of inductive bias:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to decision trees, shorter trees work better than longer ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response variable (y) in linear regression is thought to vary linearly in predictors (X).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In general, the belief that the most simplest hypothesis is more accurate than the more complicated one (Occam's razor) .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>inductive-bias</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-inductive-bias-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 19:21:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What are model training steps in machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-are-model-training-steps/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;There may exist many possible models to solve a given problem at hand. Based on your modeling decision there are usually two different ways to complete the machine learning lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;1st scenario. Training a single model with a training dataset and final evaluation with the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2nd scenario. Training multiple models with training/validation dataset and final evaluation with the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of (1st scenario), you will follow the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Divide the data into training and test sets. (Usually 70/30 splits)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select your preferable model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train it with a training dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assess the trained model in the test set. (no need to perform validation in your trained model)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of (2nd scenario), you will follow the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Divide the data into training, validation, and test sets. (Usually 50/25/25 splits)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the initial model/architecture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train the model with a training dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluate the model using the validation dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Repeat steps (b) through (d) for different models or training parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the best model based on evaluation and train the best model with combined (training + validation) datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assess the trained model in the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><category>model-evaluation</category><category>training-validation-test</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-are-model-training-steps/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:51:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>what is model training in machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-model-training-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Machine Learning model is represented by the model parameters. Those parameters are the learnable parameters. Learning happens when these parameters are updated with suitable values and the model is able to solve the given tasks.
Training is the process of feeding a training dataset to your model. The training process uses an objective function (example MSE) to get the feedback in each iteration. Since we are trying to improve the accuracy of the model on a given
input, and lower the error between model prediction and actual output, we also called training process as a model optimization process.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-model-training-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 17:59:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding and extracting hidden patterns or features from the data is the learning process in machine learning. Instead of using explicit
logic supplied by people, machine learning has the capacity to learn from experiences.
Conventional systems are created with the use of well defined human-set rules. In order for machine learning algorithms
to understand complicated patterns from inputs (x), they use outputs (y) as a feedback signal. Thus, an intelligent program is the ML system's
final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often use a logical method to solve any issue. We make an effort to break the task up into several smaller tasks and solve each smaller task
using a distinct rationale. When dealing with extremely complicated jobs, like stock price prediction, the patterns are always changing,
which has an impact on the results.
That implies that, in order to answer this problem logically, we must adjust our handwritten logic for each new change in the outputs.
Machine Learning (ML), on the other hand, creates the model using a vast amount of data. The data gives the model all of its historical experience,
which helps it better understand the pattern. We just retrain the model with fresh instances whenever the data changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 10:28:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Out-of-sample accuracy estimation using Cross validation in python and scikit-learn</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/out-of-sample-accuracy-estimation-using-cross-validation-in-python-and-scikit-learn/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will be continuing from our previous post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://sijanb.com.np/posts/k-nearest-neighbors-algorithm-using-python-and-scikit-learn/"&gt;K-Nearest Neighbors Algorithm using Python and Scikit-Learn?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting with the implementation, let's discuss few important points in cross validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Cross validation (CV), we splits our dataset into k folds (k generally setup by developer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you created k folds, you use each of the folds as test set during run and all remaining folds as train set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With cross validation, one can assess the average model performance (this post) or also for the hyperparameters selection (for example : selecting optimal neighbors size(k) in kNN) or selecting good feature
combinations from given data features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered"&gt;
&lt;div class="input"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;In [1]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="input_area"&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;math&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;collections&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Counter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;matplotlib&lt;/span&gt; inline

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# making results reproducible&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;seed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered"&gt;
&lt;div class="input"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;In [2]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="input_area"&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read_csv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'https://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/machine-learning-databases/wine/wine.data'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;','&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;columns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'CLASS'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'ALCOHOL_LEVEL'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'MALIC_ACID'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'ASH'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'ALCALINITY'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'MAGNESIUM'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'PHENOLS'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
              &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'FLAVANOIDS'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'NON_FLAVANOID_PHENOL'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'PROANTHOCYANINS'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'COLOR_INTENSITY'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
              &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'HUE'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'OD280/OD315_DILUTED'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'PROLINE'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Let us use only two features : 'ALCOHOL_LEVEL', 'MALIC_ACID' for this problem&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'CLASS'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'ALCOHOL_LEVEL'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'MALIC_ACID'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="output_wrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="output"&gt;
&lt;div class="output_area"&gt;
&lt;div class="prompt output_prompt"&gt;Out[2]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="output_html rendered_html output_subarea output_execute_result"&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;style scoped=""&gt;
    .dataframe tbody tr th:only-of-type {
        vertical-align: middle;
    }

    .dataframe tbody tr th {
        vertical-align: top;
    }

    .dataframe thead th {
        text-align: right;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="dataframe"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr style="text-align: right;"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;CLASS&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ALCOHOL_LEVEL&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;MALIC_ACID&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;0&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;3&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14.37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;4&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="1.-Cross--validation-using-Python-from-Scratch"&gt;1. Cross  validation using Python from Scratch&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="https://sijanb.com.np/posts/out-of-sample-accuracy-estimation-using-cross-validation-in-python-and-scikit-learn/#1.-Cross--validation-using-Python-from-Scratch"&gt;¶&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered"&gt;&lt;div class="prompt input_prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="inner_cell"&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sijanb.com.np/posts/out-of-sample-accuracy-estimation-using-cross-validation-in-python-and-scikit-learn/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cross-validation</category><category>kNN</category><category>machine-learning</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/out-of-sample-accuracy-estimation-using-cross-validation-in-python-and-scikit-learn/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 08:49:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>