<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CODEBUG (Posts about machine-learning-glossary)</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://sijanb.com.np/categories/machine-learning-glossary.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:sijanonly@gmail.com"&gt;Sijan Bhandari&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 19:29:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>What is Inductive Bias in Machine Learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-inductive-bias-in-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;An explicit or implicit assumption or prior information about the model that permits it to generalize
outside of the training set of data is known as inductive bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of inductive bias:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to decision trees, shorter trees work better than longer ones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response variable (y) in linear regression is thought to vary linearly in predictors (X).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In general, the belief that the most simplest hypothesis is more accurate than the more complicated one (Occam's razor) .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>inductive-bias</category><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/what-is-inductive-bias-in-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 19:21:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What are model training steps in machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-are-model-training-steps/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;There may exist many possible models to solve a given problem at hand. Based on your modeling decision there are usually two different ways to complete the machine learning lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;1st scenario. Training a single model with a training dataset and final evaluation with the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;2nd scenario. Training multiple models with training/validation dataset and final evaluation with the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of (1st scenario), you will follow the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Divide the data into training and test sets. (Usually 70/30 splits)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select your preferable model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train it with a training dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assess the trained model in the test set. (no need to perform validation in your trained model)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of (2nd scenario), you will follow the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Divide the data into training, validation, and test sets. (Usually 50/25/25 splits)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the initial model/architecture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Train the model with a training dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Evaluate the model using the validation dataset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Repeat steps (b) through (d) for different models or training parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select the best model based on evaluation and train the best model with combined (training + validation) datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assess the trained model in the test set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-are-model-training-steps/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 18:51:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What is machine learning ?</title><link>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-machine-learning/</link><dc:creator>Sijan Bhandari</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding and extracting hidden patterns or features from the data is the learning process in machine learning. Instead of using explicit
logic supplied by people, machine learning has the capacity to learn from experiences.
Conventional systems are created with the use of well defined human-set rules. In order for machine learning algorithms
to understand complicated patterns from inputs (x), they use outputs (y) as a feedback signal. Thus, an intelligent program is the ML system's
final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often use a logical method to solve any issue. We make an effort to break the task up into several smaller tasks and solve each smaller task
using a distinct rationale. When dealing with extremely complicated jobs, like stock price prediction, the patterns are always changing,
which has an impact on the results.
That implies that, in order to answer this problem logically, we must adjust our handwritten logic for each new change in the outputs.
Machine Learning (ML), on the other hand, creates the model using a vast amount of data. The data gives the model all of its historical experience,
which helps it better understand the pattern. We just retrain the model with fresh instances whenever the data changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>machine-learning</category><category>machine-learning-glossary</category><guid>https://sijanb.com.np/posts/machine-learning-glossary-what-is-machine-learning/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 10:28:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>